Modern Language Association of America, American Literature Section Papers, 1922-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Modern Language Association of America American Literature Section papers 1922-1999
Modern Language Association of America
7 linear feet Extent: 7,586 items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00903
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The American Literature Section Papers (1922-1994) were transferred from the University of Wisconsin, Madison (1985) and donated by Section members (1983-1995).
No systematic preservation of records has ever been supervised by the American Literature Section itself. Henry Pochmann, English professor at the University of Wisconsin, realized in the late 1960s that the opportunity to assemble an archive reaching back to the Section's early days was rapidly disappearing. He solicited material from all those past officers of the ALS he was able to contact, thereby forming the basis of the collection. Beginning with 1928, the collection of annual reports, committee work, and correspondence is extremely thorough. Some periods are documented by the files of several members, some by only one, but little of the Section's history seems to have been lost.
Pochmann's original collection was housed at the University of Wisconsin until 1985, when it was transferred to the Hubbell Center. By that time, newly-generated files had been coming directly to the Hubbell Center for two years. Material was not deposited regularly over the following decade, but retrospective collecting was done at the time the collection was organized into its present form.
Historical Note
The American Literature Group was formed in 1921, after the Modern Language Association (MLA) reluctantly acknowledged a growing scholarly interest in the writing of the United States. At the time such literature was studied primarily in secondary schools, and most colleges and universities had no courses on the topic. Those that did, usually offered only a single survey course. The idea that American literature could stand on its own as a discipline was viewed with skepticism, it being understood at the time as a branch of the literature of England - a branch almost wholly lacking the greatness of its parent.
The members of the new group felt that in order to prove their subject reputable, they must bring it into line with the model of disciplines that had come into being in the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries. This model was based on the empiricism of the sciences, which had been modified in English as philology, author biography, textual history, and in its furthest speculative reach, influence study. Interpretive criticism was viewed as insufficiently scholarly, the domain of the "amateurs" who had dominated writing about American literature up to this point. Similarly, some in the Group thought that it should organize a way to better train secondary school teachers in the area, but this was rejected as insufficiently academic.
The Group met each December at the annual meeting of the Modern Language Association. Many of the early papers presented under the auspices of the Group dealt with the problem of how to build a proper discipline. Work was immediately begun on bibliographies and on lists of manuscript resources and dissertations written (or needed). In 1926, as an aid to research, the field was divided into three areas: the Puritan tradition, Romanticism in American literature, and the frontier spirit. In 1928, the Group's approach was documented by the essays in The Reinterpretation of American Literature (edited by Norman Forester), which added a fourth area, realism. Efforts to establish a quarterly journal that dealt exclusively with American literature began in 1924. Duke University eventually won a small bidding war for it, and the first issue of American Literature was dated March, 1929. In 1928 a full scheme of officers and procedures was put into place with the first version of the articles of organization. This document would be periodically revised over the following decades. One project that never got off the ground was a history of American literature. Almost from its inception, the Group was dissatisfied with the existing one - The Cambridge History of American Literature (1918) - because it was written prior to the discovery of much information, gave no relative weight to different figures and genres, and had no overarching vision of the area. A committee headed by Robert Speller worked toward a plan for a new history during the thirties, but conflicting positions concerning readiness and approach caused the plan to be abandoned by 1941. (Speller proceeded with the project outside of the Group, his work resulting in The Literary History of the United States (1948).)
After World War II, with American literature firmly in place as an academic area, the Group became less central to the discipline's development. The rise of American studies in the early 1950s prompted discussion and dispute concerning the difference between cultural-historical work, and more traditional emphases on literary excellence and the humanistic approach to literature (particularly in the classroom). Insurgent movements occasionally have arisen as the Group was felt to be behind the critical times. In 1968 younger members staged a protest at the annual meeting, agitating for a direct denouncement of the Vietnam War and more explicit politics in general (particularly regarding the college students whom the professors were serving). Meanwhile the Group (which became a full-fledged MLA Section in 1966) has periodically had to fight for particular kinds of recognition and privilege within its parent organization.
A full list of the Group's/Section's Chairs and Secretaries (later Executive Coordinators) is appended to this inventory and may be used as a cross-reference with the container lists to interpret the collection's coverage of various periods and figures. A fuller listing of officers from 1921-1948 is provided in Kermit Vanderbilt's book (cited below) on pages 545-548.
For more information on the American Literature Group/Section, see the following books, parts of which were written using the American Literature Section Papers:
Kermit Vanderbilt, American Literature and the Academy (Philadelphia: U. Penn. Press, 1986)
David R. Shumway, Creating American Civilization: A Genealogy of American Literature as an Academic Discipline (Minneapolis: U. Minn. Press, 1994).
Collection Overview
The Modern Language Association, American Literature Section (ALS) Papers date from 1921 to 1993 (bulk 1928-1993).Most of the Section's records consist of correspondence saved by Secretaries or Chairs and mechanically-reproduced reports, minutes, and ballots. These last materials are contained in folders designated "Reports" and dated by year. Additionally, there are folders of material used to compile reports (such as institutional polls and other "raw" information) generated by committees, concerning the American Literature journal and Section organization, and copies of papers to be delivered at Section meetings. Correspondents include Joseph Blotner, Edward Bradley, Edwin Cady, Paul Carter, Alexander Cowie, Richard Beale Davis, Robert Falk, Benjamin Franklin Fisher, William M. Gibson, Allan Halline, Harrison Hayford, Elaine Hedges, J. Herber, High Holman, Jay B. Hubbell, Alexander Kern, Robert Edson Lee, J.A. Leo Lemay, Michael Millgate, William Mulder, Russel B. Nye, R.H. Pearce, Henry Pochmann, Walter B. Rideout, Louis D. Rubin, Robert Spiller, Willard Thorp, Arlin Turner, and James Woodress. Papers of the following individuals (past officers of the ALS), which pertain to the American Literature Group, are included in this collection: Joseph Blotner, John Gerber, Robert Edson Lee, Ernest Marchand, William Mulder, Charles Nilon, Henry Pochmann, Lewis P. Simpson, Robert Spiller, Willard Thorp, Arlin Turner, and Donald Yannella. Also, there are folders pertaining to these publications: Reinterpretation of American Literature, Eight American Authors, and American Literary Scholarship.
The folders are arranged chronologically based on the date of the earliest material contained in them. A few exceptions have been made for folders where the material is very unrepresentative of the whole. These folders are nonetheless dated by their entire span. Researchers are advised to begin with the "Reports" folders within the period that interests them, for they provide an overview of the year useful for making sense of contemporary folders of manuscript material, and in some cases indicate activities that have no documentation outside of these reports. Minutes from the December meetings sometimes occur as a discrete document and sometimes as part of a report mailed to Section members early in the following year. Since even these reports rarely contain much information that dates from later than the meeting, they have been placed in the "Reports" folders of the year of the meeting documented (i.e. reports dated early in one year appear in the folder for the previous year).
The records of the Section are augmented by the individual papers of a number of Section Chairs and Secretaries, also housed in the Hubbell Center.
Addition (00-041) (6 items, .1 lin. ft.; dated 1994-1999) includes annual reports for the ALS, 1994-1998, and a mold used to cast the Jay B. Hubbell medals.
Addition (08-267) (300 items, .3 lin. ft.; dated 1974-1987) includes records for the section’s Advisory Council over the period, as well as for the awarding of the 1986 Hubbell Medal.
Processing Note
Because the American Literature archive was created retrospectively out of a large number of separate contributions, some of which overlapped with others and some of which consisted of material separated by years or decades, it was decided that chronological interfiling made the most sense. Files generated by a single person over a discrete period were left intact and organized internally by date. If such files were donated with pre-existing separations (material relating to a particular committee, for example), those divisions were retained. To the extent that it was possible, each discrete project, committee, or body of material relating to a particular event was given its own folder, and thus title, to aid finding. If the producer of a portion of material was named or deducible, that name appears as part of the folder title. A significant part of the total material of the archive consisted of duplicate mailings, minutes, and reports. All such material was extracted, and the best copy of each was placed in that year's "Reports" folder.
Subject Headings
American Literature (Durham, N.C.); Modern Language Association of America. American Literature Group; Pound, Louise, 1872-1958; Duke University Press; Women periodical editors; Periodical editors; American literature -- History and criticism; United States -- Study and teaching
Contents of Collection
- Modern Language Association of America, American Literature Section Papers, 1922-1999
  - MLA (Modern Language Association) programs, 1924-1969, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1927-1934, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - ALG (American Literature Group) survey of members, 1925 (Box 2)
  - American Literature: Journal, 1928-1933 (Box 2)
  - Articles of Organization, pre 1932-1947 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Edward Bradley, Jay B. Hubbell, Robert Spiller), 1928-1939, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - List of masters essays on American Literature, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Papers delivered at annual MLA convention, 1921-1941 (Box 2)
  - Recommendations for the Doctorate in American Literature, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Survey: Subdivision of the field of American Literature, 1927 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1942, (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - Annual meeting papers listed, 1937-1945 (Box 3)
  - Committee on a Cooperative Literary History, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Materials of American Literary History, 1941-1942, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (Alexander Cowie, Jay B. Hubbell, Henry Pochmann), 1939-1946, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Dissertations in American Literature (1930-1940),1940 (Box 3)
  - Organization of ALG, 1942-1945 (Box 3)
  - The Present State of Scholarship in American Literary History, report, 1942 (Box 3)
  - 1943-1948, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - American Literature: Journal, 1945-1963 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence in Re-Anthology of American Literature (Henry Pochmann Mss.), 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Allan Halline, Willard Thorp), 1946-1949, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Curricula in American Civilization and American Literature in the College Curriculum (Willard Thorp Mss.), 1947-1951 (Box 4)
  - The Teaching of American Literature:
    - Summary report, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Survey responses, 1946, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1949-1953, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Best 20 American Works Survey, ca. 1949 (Box 5)
  - Committee on Library Manuscript Holdings (Ernest Marchand Mss.), 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Committee on Trends in Research in American Literature (Arlin Turner Mss.), 1951-1953 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (Jay B. Hubbell, Henry Pochmann, Robert Spiller, Arlin Turner), 1949-1957, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Trends in Research in American Literature, 1940-1950: Report, 1951 (Box 5)
  - 1954-1959, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - American Studies Association and Society for American Studies (Robert Spiller Mss.): Chronologies to 1954 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Library Manuscript Holdings (Ernest Marchand Mss.), 1953-1961, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence (Robert Falk, Alexander Kern), 1954-1960, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Nominating Committee (Richard Adams), 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - 1960-1965, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Change from "Group" to "Section" of MLA (Henry Pochmann Mss.), 1962-1963 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Alexander Kern, Robert Spiller, James Woodress), 1961-1965, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Nominating Committee, 1962-1965 (Box 7)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Paul Carter, Arlin Turner, J. Herber, R.H. Pearce, Henry Pochmann, Robert Spiller, James Woodress), 1965-1981, (8 folders) (Box 8)
  - Foerster Prize Committee (Henry Pochmann Mss.), 1966 (Box 8)
  - Papers delivered at the ALS meeting (Henry Pochmann Mss.), 1966 (Box 8)
  - Re: Reinterpretation of American Literature (1928): Correspondence and Essay (Robert Falk, Robert Spiller Mss.), 1928-1966 (Box 8)
  - Those Early Days Essay (Robert Spiller Mss.), 1966 (Box 8)
  - 1968-1969, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - American Literature Section:
    - Archives Planning, 1968-1972 (Box 9)
    - Group I: Early American, 1968-1969 (Box 9)
    - Group II: 19th Century, 1968-1969, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - American Literature: Journal, 1967-1969 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence (Paul Carter, Henry Pochmann), 1968, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Eight American Authors Revision, 1968-1970 (Box 9)
  - Foerster Prize Committee (John Gerber Mss.), 1969 (Box 9)
  - Manuscript Holdings Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 9)
  - Proposed seminar on "Afro-American Bibliography," 1969 (Box 9)
  - Re: Politics at 1968 MLA business meeting, 1969 (Box 9)
  - 20th Century American Literature Seminar, 1968-1969 (Box 9)
  - 1970 (Box 10)
  - American Literature Section (ALS):
    - Group I: Early American 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - Group II: 19th Century, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Group III: Realism, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - Group IV: 20th Century, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
  - American Literature abstracts, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Paul Carter, Harrison Hayford, High Holman, Robert Edson Lee), (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Foerster Prize (to Nathalia Wright), 1970 (Box 10)
  - Program Planning: Correspondence, 1970 (Box 10)
  - 1971-1972, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Robert Edson Lee, Michael Millgate, William Mulder), (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Duke Press, 1970-1973, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Financial Records: (Box 12)
    - 1974-1976, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Accounts, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Financial Records:
    - Bank statements, 1974-1975 (Box 12)
    - Security Bank and U. Colorado Accounts, 1970-1971, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - University of Utah Computer Account (Box 12)
  - 1973-1974, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Ballots and membership forms, 1974-1976 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence:
    - American Literary Scholarship (William Mulder Mss.), 1974-1975 (Box 13)
    - (Robert Edson Lee Mss.), 1973 (Box 13)
    - With MLA, 1974 (Box 13)
    - Membership, 1973-1975 (Box 13)
    - With Richard Beale Davis (William Mulder Mss.), 1974-1975 (Box 13)
    - With Louis D. Rubin (William Mulder Mss.), 1974-1975 (Box 13)
  - Membership materials, 1973 (Box 13)
  - NEH Bicentennial Grant, 1974 (Box 13)
  - 1975-1979, (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - ALS/MLA relations, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence:
    - Membership, 1976-1978, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - (William Mulder Mss.), 1976-1979 (Box 14)
    - With William M. Gibson (William Mulder Mss.), 1978 (Box 14)
    - With Russel B. Nye (William Mulder Mss.), 1975-1977 (Box 14)
    - With Nathalia Wright (William Mulder Mss.), 1977 (Box 14)
    - (Charles Nilon Mss.), 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - With Edwin Cady (Charles Nilon Mss.) 1979-1981 (Box 14)
  - Duke Press, 1974-1981, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Nominating Committee (William Mulder Mss.), 1975-1976 (Box 14)
  - Paper abstracts, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Use of the ALS mailing list, 1976-1977 (Box 14)
  - 1980-1985, (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - ALS/MLA relations, 1981-1982 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence:
    - 1982 (Box 15)
    - Joseph Blotner, Mss.), 1981 (Box 15)
    - Charles Nilon Mss.), 1979-1981 (Box 15)
    - With Joseph Blotner (Charles Nilon, Mss.), 1981 (Box 15)
    - With Walter B. Rideout (Charles Nilon Mss.), 1980-1981 (Box 15)
    - (Lewis P. Simpson Mss.), 1983 (Box 15)
  - Duke Press (Donald Yannella Mss.), 1982 (Box 15)
  - 1986-1993, (8 folders) (Box 16)
  - Correspondence (Benjamin Franklin Fisher, Elaine Hedges, J.A. Leo Lemay), 1986-1990, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Hubbell Award Committee records, 1966-1993, (20 folders) (Box 17)
    RESTRICTED: Box is restricted
- Addition (2000-0041), 1994-1999, (1 box)
  Addition (00-041) (6 items, .1 lin. ft.; dated 1994-1999) includes annual reports for the ALS, 1994-1998, and a mold used to cast the Jay B. Hubbell medals.
  - Annual reports and mold for medals (Box 1)
- Addition (2008-0267), 1974-1987, (1 box)
  Addition (08-267) (300 items, .3 lin. ft.; dated 1974-1987) includes records for the section’s Advisory Council over the period, as well as for the awarding of the 1986 Hubbell Medal.
  - Advisory Council and Hubbell Medal records (Box 1)